Mendershausen, Horst; Papers ger128
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Horst Mendershausen Papers
1930-1999
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger128
0.6 cubic ft.
The Horst Mendershausen Papers consist of select materials from six decades of Mendershausen's personal and professional life as an economist and political scientist.
Biographical History
Born in Koethen, Germany in 1911, Horst Mendershausen obtained his Ph.D. from the University of Geneva in 1937 and received a Rockefeller Fellowship for post-graduate study in Norway and the United States the following year. During Dr. Mendershausen's long career in economics and politics, he served as a professor at Bennington College; an economist at the Federal Reserve Bank; an economist and assistant chief of price control for the U.S. Military Government for Germany in Berlin in the immediate post-World War II years; a consultant for the United Nations Division of Economic Stability and Development; a lecturer at the University of California, Los Angeles; and as a senior social scientist and later a consultant for The RAND Corporation. He authored numerous books, articles, and reports, some published by The RAND Corporation.
Dr. Mendershausen died in 2003 and was survived by his wife Elfriede and sons Philip and Ralph.
Scope and Contents
The Horst Mendershausen Papers contain biographical materials, correspondence, reports, lectures, university commencement speeches, declassified United States military documents, and subject files related to his publications, article reprints, and clippings.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series and is arranged alphabetically.
Acquisition Information
Horst Mendershausen's son Ralph Mendershausen donated all the materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2016, 2021, 2022 and 2023.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred six monographs: Changes in Income Distribution during the Great Depression by Horst Mendershausen, Coping with the Oil Crisis by Horst Mendershausen, Der Deutsche Dichter um die Jahrhundertwende und Seine Abgelostheit von der Gesellschaft by Hans Wilhelm Rosenhaupt, Die Ostbeziehungen der Europaischen Gemeinschaft by Eberhard Schulz, Les Variations du Mouvement Saisonnier Dans L'Industrie de la Construction by Horst Mendershausen, and Two Postwar Recoveries of the German Economy by Horst Mendershausen to the book division of Special Collections. They will be catalogued and included in the University Library Catalog.
Political Science; Economics; Economists--United States; Political scientists--United States; Files by subject; Correspondence; Germans--United States.; Jews -- Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees; Mendershausen, Horst
- A Plan for the Liquidation of War Finance and the Financial Rehabilitation of Germany, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- ARPLAN: Bericht über die Studienreise nach der Sowjet-Union, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Changes in Income Distribution During the Great Depression, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Consultant for Rand, 1973-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Coping with Oil Crisis, 1975-1975; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1937; 1939; 1967; 1969; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1978; 1981; 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence and Writings, 1943-1949; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence and Writings-Ostrander and Kindleberger, 1947; 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence with Bernard Taurer, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Datebook, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Lectures and Academic Writing, 1939-1942; 1946-1948; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Neu Beginnen, 1940-1996; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Personal Correspondence and Reviews of Doctoral Dissertation, 1939-1946; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Personal Documents, 1930-1990; Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Polanyi Book, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Two German Recoveries-Book Reviews, 1955-1959; 1972; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Western European Power-Correspondence and Reviews, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)